<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Lucas Viana's ruminations</title><link>https://lucas-viana.com/</link><description>Recent content on Lucas Viana's ruminations</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 16:36:48 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lucas-viana.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Learn `sed` and be happy</title><link>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2022-07-05-sed/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 16:36:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2022-07-05-sed/</guid><description>When you&amp;rsquo;re done reading this article, you&amp;rsquo;ll be ready to become a sed expert. Yes, you read it right &amp;ndash; So let&amp;rsquo;s hit the ground running.
What is sed? Ever wanted to edit a file without having to open it in a text editor? Or maybe you want to modify several files and don&amp;rsquo;t want to do it manually?
With sed, you just issue a short command in the terminal and bam!</description></item><item><title>Character encodings: ASCII, UTF-8, Unicode and what is Latin-1?</title><link>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-11-21-character-encoding/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 16:36:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-11-21-character-encoding/</guid><description>What is Unicode, why is it used everywhere, and what are the options?
We, software developers need to use string data types pretty much daily and yet, there is a lot under the surface that nowadays we don&amp;rsquo;t even think about anymore. This makes character encodings a basic thing, but is it simple?
Encoding, you say? So let&amp;rsquo;s start from the beginning, what is &amp;ldquo;enconding&amp;rdquo;, really?
To encode is to convert one type of data into another type.</description></item><item><title>The down and dirty of UTF-16</title><link>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-12-25-utf16/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 16:36:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-12-25-utf16/</guid><description>This is part 3 of a series of posts on Unicode and encodings:
Part 1: What the heck is Unicode Part 2: The down and dirty of UTF-8 Part 3: The down and dirty of UTF-16 A very short background At the end of the &amp;rsquo;80s, there were two competing forces for standardizing character sets: ISO 10646 and Unicode. ISO was idealistic and Unicode was pragmatic. ISO created a character set containing more than 2 billion code points (of course, most were not allocated).</description></item><item><title>The down and dirty of UTF-8</title><link>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-12-25-utf8/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 16:36:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/2021-12-25-utf8/</guid><description>What the double UTF is UTF-8? Let&amp;rsquo;s lay it down, bit-by-bit.
Unicode and UTF-8 In my [previous post]({% post_url 2021-11-21-character-encoding %}), we dug a little deeper into the reasons to be for Unicode and found out that Unicode is an immense character table containing all the characters in the world. Or at least a valiant attempt at that. This table has 1 112 064 rows, and each row is a code point (i.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/sed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lucas-viana.com/posts/sed/</guid><description>What is sed? Ever wanted to edit a file without having to open it in a text editor? Or maybe you want to modify several files and don&amp;rsquo;t want to do it manually?
With sed, you just issue a short command in the terminal and bam!, you&amp;rsquo;ve changed the contents of a file. You can see it as CTRL+R on super steroyds. sed is capable of doing simple search and replace (regex based), delete lines, add lines or even reverse the lines of a file.</description></item></channel></rss>